What would you risk to make a difference?
Shooting Dogs is a drama, history film directed by Michael Caton-Jones.
Two westerners, a priest and a teacher find themselves in the middle
of the Rwandan genocide and face a moral dilemna.
Do they place themselves in danger and protect the
refugees, or escape the country with their lives?
Based on a true story.
Christopher, played by John Hurt.
Joe Connor, played by Hugh Dancy.
Capitaine Charles Delon, played by Dominique Horwitz.
Rachel, played by Nicola Walker.
François, played by David Gyasi.
Roland, played by Steve Toussaint.
Shooting Dogs, released in the United States as Beyond the Gates, is a 2005 film directed by
Michael Caton-Jones and starring John Hurt, Hugh Dancy and Clare-Hope Ashitey.
It is based on the experiences of BBC news producer David Belton,
who worked in Rwanda during the Rwandan genocide.
Belton is the film's co-writer and one of its producers.
The setting of the film is the École Technique Officielle (ETO) in
Kigali, Rwanda, in 1994, during the Rwandan genocide.
Hurt plays a Catholic priest (loosely based on Vjekoslav Ćurić) and Dancy an English
teacher, both Europeans, who are caught up in the events of the genocide.
Unlike Hotel Rwanda, which was filmed in South Africa using South African actors,
the film was shot in the original location of the scenes it portrays.
Also, many of the massacre survivors were employed as part of
the production crew and in minor acting roles.
The film's title refers to the actions of UN soldiers in shooting at
the stray dogs that scavenged the bodies of the dead.
Since the UN soldiers were not allowed to shoot at the Hutu extremists who had caused the deaths in the first place,
the shooting of dogs is symbolic of the madness of the situation that the film attempts to capture.
The film explores themes of destruction of a
civilization, rape, civil war, hutu, tutsi.
The tone is emotional.